welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we call hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
Isiah so you had a question about
initiation video games of masculinity
yeah sorry yeah yeah on the previous
situational assessment that you did you
mentioned something about how kids
playing Minecraft a lot of untapped
potential to deal with like the issues
in the meadow crisis and I've recently
read a lot of them Jungian thinkers like
Robert Wise iron John comes to mind
where they diagnose the crisis of
masculine is lacking initiation rituals
from boyhood to manhood so I'm wondering
if you have any suggestions on how Gen X
or little men can sort of build that
framework for the young generation I
guess another way of putting it is how
can we bring teenagers into the campfire
that's a really good question that's a
big deal and I liked what you actually
named it in terms of Gen X and
Millennials and teenagers right because
there's something about the phases of
life that are different
how do you this
you're on mute 31 31 how many kids you
got
I don't have kids all right so you and I
are sort of somewhat the different
positions in terms of the this arc of
life and there's a couple of folks here
look like they're you know my senior and
pop a couple folks maybe your junior
then man oh man it sure is the case that
we dropped the ball on that isn't it
like the degree to which we we didn't
just not initiate people into adulthood
we sort of did exactly opposite in every
possible way so we've got a lot of
catching up to do and I got to really
say I have a bad feeling and I apologize
for that bad feeling but I had a bad
feeling that
my elders they're the ones who had an
opportunity to actually have what's
called intergenerational transmission
but for whatever reason chose to step
away from that and did not rebuild it in
a new way daliyah stood it to my
awareness so we're kind of happy to go
inside we can't rely on rituals or
traditions they've been handed down to
us because that if originals traditions
were handed down to us or our
handed-down had dropped and left behind
or so out of place that we don't know
how to use them well then we can recover
stuff from from older environments
there's actually some pretty good stuff
out there that other cultures still do
and use but we should be careful not to
simulate and I use I often times refer
to the folks who we're way too many
feathers I mean if you know what I'm
talking about
I'm gonna call that a certain simulation
but there are lots of good things that
exist in lots of cultures around the
world understand how to do this thing
well what I would say is that here's
more or less than nature the beasts each
of us as kind of cohorts the boomers the
Xers the Millennials and Gen Z have sort
of like a generational crisis that has
to do with something like the the thing
that we have to get over to some extent
the boomers have to get over and I'm
just gonna call it narcissism and it has
to do with something like I mean can we
look like a Frank when they were young
they were golden children right and
everything whether they as individuals I
think everybody's an individual their
life arc is individuals quite diverse
but as a generation things kind of
worked out they have an embodied sense
of things kind of working out but
neither into life and by the way with
this virus that may be closer into life
and they maybe thought they were gonna
be and it's the ability to turn their
attention towards what is in fact the
legacy of their generation to recognize
that they probably don't have a lot in
the terms of let's call it know-how
you say their expertise is expertise
associate with an environment that is
increasingly in the past but they have a
whole lot in terms of wisdom now so I'm
not really that interested in most cases
that in all cases in your institutional
knowledge I don't really care that much
about how the Federal Reserve works
because it's going to go away real quick
I care a whole lot about life I care a
whole lot about meaning I care a whole
lot about how what it was actually like
back in the day when communities really
existed and people really cared for each
other
what is actually valuable where she
would be orienting our attention what
really matters my elders
elder I need the elders to elder so then
he got my cohort he's poor
slackers of Gen X we got to get over to
ourselves and stop being me lists and we
just have to actually step in and say
okay some of us have actually built a
capacity to have some level of
effectiveness in the moment and most of
us have skin in the game and we actually
have kids do we care about so we have an
embodied relationship with our own
bodies have competence and expertise but
our biological bodies put us very much
in the this thing needs to happen but in
many ways we also don't really know what
to do we're behind the curve so we need
to support we need to put ourselves in a
support role to help the Millennials do
the things that folks in the end of the
day the loads gonna fall in the
Millennials to make this thing happen
then it just needs to be clear all right
so the Millennials responsibility and
dr. Jordan Peterson I think showed up as
a teleportation from this future for
better or for worse but he shook a whole
lot of people into recognizing that as
the Millennial crisis balls in your
hands guys step up it's all there is to
it take about what happened in World War
two all right in World War two a whole
bunch of 20 and 25 year old kids got
thrown right in the middle of
machine-gun bullets they had to carry
these responsibility for the war in
their bodies and if they didn't the
whole thing was over right it wasn't
wasn't there the equivalent of Gen X and
the Boomers Franklin Roosevelt was doing
fireside chats and Patton was sitting
back behind the back lines trying to
help people make good choices it was the
kids in the front lines who were
actually tearing most of the load that's
kind of where we are now but of course
our front lines are spiritual
frontlines and community frontlines and
relearning how to do those things from
scratch now in some sense you have the
enormous advantage that our educational
systems complete shit-shit which to say
they didn't train you very well which
means you can just kind of throw it out
the backdoor and relearn really quickly
on the other hand the reality is that
the Millennials have an incredible level
of capacity like extraordinary level of
capacity both in terms of just sheer
smarts and also in terms of like heart
the ball we dropped in certain training
masculinity actually built up capacities
and young men that we would not have
otherwise had now my generation doesn't
have a lot of the capacities that your
generation has that are going to be
needful right now and things like
empathy and self-awareness and EQ just
talk to a like a real actual boomer man
and get a sense of how fragile the EQ
was of that particular generation so
take those capacities and then reboot
that with a new new sensibility of what
a new masculinity masculinity looks like
and recognize that just imagine that
you're you are going to be responsible
for a family what does that feel like
what does it mean to prepare a territory
where you actually take responsibility
for the area around you what does it
mean to actually identify in your body
the feeling of other men who can
actually stand arm and arm your shoulder
and shoulder and turn themselves towards
the threat and stand and have it break
against them right if you can feel that
energy that's the energy to get into now
we've got the other side we've been
talking a lot about men but this is of
course fundamentally about female crisis
let's be very clear the feminine energy
is that which is being called up in the
hardest level across all generations I
don't even know what that looks like I
just know it's the case I can feel it
every time I feel it in my wife for
example and she digs deeper and deeper
and deeper into learning how to discover
in herself the anchor grounding there's
actually a really good story it's the
very first chapter of The Grapes of
Wrath anybody read them
it's like it's exactly the situation
alright so it looks like this it's like
maybe even like the first three three
paragraphs he Steinbeck talks about the
you know it's the this the Okies the the
the sharecroppers and the men they go
out and they they put their hands in the
dirt and they sift it they look at the
sky and they look at the crops and they
chat with each other and trying to kind
of figure out what's going on and the
women they're inside in the house right
there they're holding the family and
they're holding the heart and holding
the the grounding and they're looking
and watching but then something happens
or suddenly you just get this moment
where suddenly the woman goes we're
leavin she makes the call that this
watering hole is no longer valid your
responsibility is now shifted from
trying to make those crops work to
getting this family to somewhere
somewhere safe all right
and of course as soon as she says it you
can see the man just drops what he's
doing in pivots I don't know if you've
been married but by the way that's how
it works so that's kind of it and by the
way just learning how to do that at the
simple level is a really good practice
and a lot of people that happen to be
forced to learn that right now because
we're no longer able it'll really really
distract ourselves with work and school
and hopefully media and having to
relearn how to just be in relationship
with the people we happen to be stuck in
quarantine win but that's simple stuff
of right relationship between the
masculine and feminine the right
relationship between men and women which
aren't necessarily exactly the same
thing is a big part of the nature of
this Christ it's a two degree to which
we learn that and relearn that and
rebuild capacities by interacting with
other people and learning what works and
what doesn't work and deal with our own
fear and fear of limitations in
ourselves and grow through it as rapidly
as possible this also begins to talk
about what Joe is talking about I think
I've rambled on at length on that I
apologize